Today's דף *daf* is צ"ג *Tzadi Gimmel*. We pick up with some
משנה Mishnah, *mishna* wrapping up issues about the rights of the workers
to eat, and we pick up with the משנה Mishnah *mishna* about
the second wide line. קוצץ אדם על ידי al yedei עצמו על
ידי al yedei בנו ובתו הגדולים על ידי עבדו ושפחתו הגדולים *Kotetz
adam al yedei atzmo al yedei bno u'vito ha'gdolim al yedei avdo
u'shifchato ha'gdolim*. So we've seen actually 90% of this משנה Mishnah. *mishna*
we've seen was addressed yesterday. It was quoted and discussed yesterday. So
a person can sort of stipulate for himself and for his adult
children and for his wife, על ידי אשתו *al yedei ishto*, and
for his adult slaves, and basically stipulate that they won't eat in
negotiating for different type for higher wages. מפני שיש בהן דעת *mipnei
she-yesh bahen da'at* because they have, you know, דעת *da'at*, they have
thought, intelligence, and therefore they can legally, you know, make this deal.
They can waive their rights in order to get a higher pay,
and they're implicitly sort of deputizing him to represent them. אבל aval
אינו קוצץ על ידי בנו ובתו הקטנים ועל ידי עבדו ושפחתו הכנענים
ועל ידי בהמתו *aval eino kotetz al yedei bno u'vito ha'ktanim v'al
yedei avdo u'shifchato ha'kna'anim v'al yedei behemto*. He cannot do it on
behalf of his minor children because his minor children have a right
to eat and he can't negotiate that
away, and they can't give it away.
And this fits in very well with the idea that we, you
know, we had different ways of explaining it, but the easiest way
to explain it is משמיא הוא זכה *mi-shmaya hu zachah*. It's not
seen as part of their salary, it's seen as part of a
type of a special right that the תורה Torah *Torah* gives them.
And therefore, the person himself or herself can forgo that right, but
you can't forgo it for them
if they're minors there. ועל ידי עבדו ושפחתו הקטנים *v'al yedei avdo
u'shifchato ha'ktanim*, the minor slaves, same issue, even though he's entitled to
their labor, this is not seen as pay for the labor, this
is seen as a basic right that the תורה Torah *Torah* gives
them. ועל ידי בהמתו *v'al yedei behemto*, and not for his animal,
that I'll hire my animal to you, you'll pay a higher rent,
it won't eat, you'll muzzle it, מפני שאין בהם דעת *mipnei she-ein
bahem da'at* for the reason we said, that they do not have
their own will and דעת *da'at* and intelligence that the הלכה halacha?
*halacha* recognizes. And therefore they cannot forgo the right that the תורה
Torah *Torah* has given them, and you certainly and you can't forgo
it for them because it's not like a salary that you're entitled
to. You, the owner or the father, are entitled to. The animal
is a different reason, although it puts them all in the same
category, but as רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, the animal is not just
about a question about monetary negotiations. You can't even muzzle your own
animal. So it's not just sort of some type of a, you
could say the reason is because, you know, your animal isn't in
a position to give away its right. I mean it's interesting to
sort of think about that in similar lines. Okay, but it's not
just about the question about what the person who you're hired to
owes you. An animal is essentially always hired to the person, the
owner or anybody who's using it, and therefore they cannot take this
away. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, השוכר
את הפועלים *ha-socher et ha-po'alim* in the משנה Mishna? *mishna*, לעשות בנטע
רבעי שלו *la'asot b'neta revai shelo*. We also quoted this yesterday. If
you hire them to work with your fourth-year plantings, which basically you
can't eat the fruit, and they didn't realize it, they thought they
were going to be entitled to it, הרי אלו לא יאכלו *harei
elu lo yocheilu*. They can't eat because obviously it can't be eaten
out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. אם לא הודיעם *im lo hodiam*, but if
he didn't inform them and they thought they were going to be
entitled to eat and now they find out that they're
not, so in that case פודה ומאכילן *podeh u'ma'achilan*. You redeem the
fruit and you allow them to eat from it. נתפרסו עיגוליו נתפתחו
חביותיו *nitparsu igulav nitpatchu chaviyotav*. If his rounds of pressed figs sort
of, you know, broke and scattered. Now the point here is that
it's after the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha, *gmar melacha*, but it got
reverted to a state where somebody would see it and think it
would be before גמר מלאכה gmar melacha, *gmar melacha* and therefore entitled
to eat from it. Or נתפתחו חביותיו *nitpatchu chaviyotav*, the barrels were
opened and they had to be resealed. הרי אלו לא יאכלו *harei
elu lo yocheilu*. They can't eat because it's after the גמר מלאכה
gmar melacha, *gmar melacha*. It's already obligated in מעשר ma’aser, *ma'aser*. אם
לא הודיעם *im lo hodiam*, but if you didn't tell them and
they were expecting that they would be able to eat, and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discussed yesterday how could it be that they could
look at this and reasonably expect that it had not been finished,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gave various scenarios. In that case מעשר Ma'aser.
ומאכילן *me'aser u'ma'achilan*. You have to take מעשר *ma'aser* and let them
eat from it because now it's obligated in מעשר *ma'aser*. So you
take the מעשר *ma'aser* and you let them eat from it. שומרי
פירות shomrei peirot. *shomrei peirot*. Now the one new thing that we
haven't discussed yet, and the only reason this is not new to
us is because we spent a lot of yesterday discussing it. So
the one new thing we haven't discussed yet is שומרי פירות אוכלים
מהלכות מדינה Me'hilchos Medina. אבל לא מן התורה Min HaTorah... *shomrei peirot
ochlin me-hilchot medina aval lo min ha-Torah*. People that watch fruit are
entitled to eat because that's the practice. It's an interesting phrase, הלכות
מדינה Hilchos Medina, *hilchot medina*, but it picks up on, you know,
הכל כמנהג המדינה *ha'kol k'minhag ha'medina*, which we had like a פרק
perek *perek* ago. I believe it was a פרק *perek* ago. Anyway,
so but it's interesting that it becomes the word הלכות halachot, *hilchot*,
right, which הלכה *halacha* we understand as like religious law, but here
it just means the standard practices of the country. So the standard
practices of the land were to allow people who watch, you know,
the fruit, and to eat from it. But הלכתית halachically *halachically* they're
not really entitled to it. Now why are they not הלכתית halachically
*halachically* entitled to it? So that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* turns to.
We'll have two explanations. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. Rabbi Bloomstine, just a quick question. Yeah. It's bothered me all
day yesterday. The phrase על ידי here means something different than what
it usually means, right? Because על ידי usually means through the agency
of, so someone else would do something. Right, you're right. It's funny,
it's like reversing who, right, right. It's a strange idiom. Right, על
ידי here means on behalf of, not through something. That's correct, that's
correct. שומרי פירות. So, why do people who watch fruit, why are
they not הלכתית halachically entitled to eat from it? אמר רב, Amar
Rav, לא שנו אלא שומרי גנות ופרדסים. lo shanu ela shomrei gannot
u’pardesim. They are watching fruit that is still attached to the ground.
They're watching orchards or vegetable gardens. Now, if it's attached to the
ground, pop quiz, when are you allowed, when is a worker allowed
to eat when he's dealing with stuff that's growing from the ground?
Only at what stage? Anybody? Nobody remembers? When it's growing from the
ground, you're only entitled to eat when it's the
גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, when you're doing the harvesting itself. Okay? So
if it's growing and you're watching the vineyard or the orchard or
the garden and the stuff is on the trees and on the
vines, it's not the גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha so you're not entitled
to eat. So that's why you're not הלכתית halachically entitled, it has
to be a special practice of the of the country, a standard
practice. Okay? That's only שומרי גנות ופרדסים. shomrei gannot u’pardesim. אבל שומרי
גתות וערמות, Aval shomrei gatot va’areimot, let's say you're watching it after
the stuff has been harvested. You're watching the wine in the vats
or you're watching the cut bundles of wheat. In that case, okay,
it is after it's been cut, but presumably that's not yet the
גמר מלאכה, Gmar Melacha okay, even though certainly by the bundles of
wheat now it'd have to be threshed and winnowed the whole thing.
Even the wine we talked about the fact that maybe it's not
enough that it's in the vat, you have to remove the leaves
or whatever it might be. So that case, it's cut and it's
not yet גמר מלאכה, Gmar Melacha so in that case you are
entitled to eat. In that case, אוכל מן התורה, ochel min ha-Torah,
you are entitled to eat. Okay? So according to רב, Rav, the
difference is the only reason that they were not הלכתית halachically entitled
here was because it was before the fruit was harvested and you
were not dealing with the and you were not actually doing the
harvesting. Yes? You can repeat that one thing when it's attached to
the ground. When it's attached, when it's ready to be picked, you
only eat as you're harvesting it. When you're harvesting, when it's attached
to the ground. After it's been harvested, you eat until it gets
to the stage of obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u’ma’asrot. So רב
Rav says if you're watching the garden after it's been harvested and
picked and it's not yet obligated in תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u’ma’asrot, then
you're הלכתית entitled to eat.
Okay, קסבר, kasavar, רב Rav is of the opinion משמר כעושה מעשה
דמי, mishamer k’oseh ma’aseh dami, that the problem here was not the
act of watching. Watching fruit is just as much of doing a
מלאכה melacha with fruit as picking it or as weeding it. Okay?
You're still, you know, that's considered doing a מלאכה. melacha. And therefore
the only question whether you're entitled to eat is: is it the
right time or not? If it's before it's harvested, it's not the
right time, and if it's after it's harvested or whatever it is,
the right time. But basically the act of watching is like any
other type of tending to a fruit, you know, to a caring
for the
dealing whatever doing a labor with with the fruit as anything else.
ושמואל אמר, U’Shmuel amar, ושמואל v’Shmuel says לא שנו אלא שומרי גתות
וערמות. lo shanu ela shomrei gatot va’areimot. No, no, no. He disagrees.
He says the only time you're entitled to eat even from the
communal practice is when you're watching it after it's been harvested. Now
the question is: wait a minute, after it's been harvested, why aren't
you הלכתית entitled to, right? It's after it's been harvested and it's
not yet גמר מלאכה Gmar Melacha for מעשר, so what's going to
be the issue here? So let's take a look. אבל שומרי גנות
ופרדסים, Aval shomrei gannot u’pardesim, what as it's growing and you're not
actually doing the harvesting itself, אין אוכלים, ein ochlim, you don't eat,
לא מן התורה ולא מהלכות מדינה, lo min ha-Torah v’lo mei-hilchot medinah,
not from the Torah law and not from even the norms of
the country. And by the way, I should say that the גמרא's
Gemara going to make clear later that what שמואל's Shmuel saying is
that even if you're doing something that's a more direct labor with
it, let's say you're weeding the trees, you know, you're weeding the
vegetable garden, nevertheless, if it's before the time of harvest, then you
have no right to eat. The only time you have to eat
is after the harvest, and even then it's after the harvest when
you're watching it. So the question is: wait a minute, if it's
after the harvest and you're watching it, why aren't you from the
תורה Torah: allowed to eat?
No, it's harvest, it's after the harvest. And he says, so that's
why שמואל Shmuel says, we're talking about after the harvest and you're
watching it, so why not? So the גמרא Gemara: says, קסבר, kasavar,
he's of the opinion משמר לאו כעושה מעשה דמי, mishamer lav k’oseh
ma’aseh dami, that watching something is not really like working with the
fruit. The תורה Torah, only entitles you to eat when you're working
with the fruit. Okay, so walking around the garden with your, you
know, and making sure nobody enters into the garden, that's not a
real direct engagement with the fruit. And therefore, you know, what you're
doing is a little external to the fruit. It's to protect the
fruit, but what you're doing is external to the fruit.
Right, that's true, but there's much of a more like with each,
you know, you're working around every individual piece and so on. Right.
So this is much more distant. Okay? So that's שמואל's Shmuel position.
All right? So basically.
Right, if you think about it actually, we had a tree there,
but okay, let's deal with it. You've got your tree, you've got
your apples tree, okay? So this is, okay, then the apples are
picked, okay? So this is like what this is, I don't know
why I had one upside down, okay. This is the time of
the
harvest, black apples. Actually,
yeah, sure, actually picking an apple, okay? So anyway, so this is
when it's מחובר, Mechubar, and you can only eat here at the
time of גמר מלאכה gmar melachah, or harvesting.
Okay. Then it is picked and then you could actually eat until
it's, well, you know, this is not a great example because most
because most fruit that's actually the גמר מלאכה gmar melachah. itself. All
right, fine. So let's have your standing wheat.
I don't know if that's supposed to look like wheat, but whatever.
Okay, anyway, okay,
I don't know. Anyway, that's that's my sis. Does that look like
a sis? Okay, anyway, okay, okay, so anyway, okay, so then you've
got your bundles of wheat here.
Okay, now it's been harvested. This is when you eat. This is
stage one. Now that it's תלוש, Taloosh, you eat all the way
until this point until you've got it basically like in the גורן,
Goren, this case of like a גמר מלאכה gmar melachah. for מעשר.
Okay.
So that's when you can eat. When can you eat? You can
basically eat from this point to this point. Okay, that's when you're
allowed to eat. So now if you are basically, okay, so if
you're doing anything, if you're being שומר Shomer here, if you're being
a שומר, Shomer,
you're just watching the wheat, okay? So you're not yet allowed to
eat. Okay, because of that you're not allowed to eat. Okay, if
you're here being a שומר, Shomer,
you should be allowed to eat, except the question is, is it
considered like you're doing labor with the wheat or not? Okay, that's
the question. So רב Rav says, all right,
רב Rav says watching it is like doing labor. So here, this
is like you're doing labor with it, except it's too early. But
nevertheless, you're entitled to eat מן התורה... Min HaTorah you're entitled to
eat from the practices of the country. Here, you're doing labor with
it according to רב Rav you'd be entitled to eat מן התורה
Min HaTorah. because you're doing labor during the time when you're allowed
to eat. Okay, so רב Rav says this is like you're doing
labor with it. This is הלכות מדינה, Hilchos Medina. this is מן
התורה. Min HaTorah. שמואל Shmuel says this is not like you're really
doing labor with the thing. So at this stage, you're not entitled
to eat. And שמואל Shmuel says even if you were weeding at
this stage, you're not entitled to eat. Nobody's entitled to eat before
the time. Okay, and I don't care even if you're doing real
מלאכה, Melacha, even if you're weeding. At this stage, you would be
entitled to eat from הלכות מדינה. Hilchos Medina You're not really entitled
to eat from the תורה Torah. because that's not real labor, okay,
but from הלכות מדינה Hilchos Medina you are. All right, so that's
basically the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Yes? Did I
know what I'm talking about שבת? Shabbat? But when רב Rav says
that watching is like מלאכה, Melacha, does he mean that you actually
could not have watched it on שבת? Shabbat? No, no, no, it's
totally unrelated. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: שמואל Shmuel
says also from הלכות מדינה hilchos medinah you can't eat. Here, you
can't eat according to שמואל. Shmuel. Okay. According to רב, Rav, רב
Rav says here you eat מהלכות מדינה. Me'hilchos Medina. Right? And here,
and here you eat מן התורה. Min HaTorah, Okay, actually, since we're
using blue to mean מן התורה, Min HaTorah.
we'll keep that the same. So רב Rav says here you eat
מן התורה. min haTorah. Okay. And here you eat מהלכות מדינה. Me'hilchos
Medina. That's what רב Rav says. Right. Okay. And שמואל Shmuel says
no, here you don't eat at all because it's too early, and
here you eat מהלכות מדינה. Me'hilchos Medina. Why does it say אינם
אוכלים לא מן התורה ולא מהלכות מדינה? Einam ochlim lo min HaTorah
v'lo me'hilchos Medina? Here,
here is when you אינם אוכלים לא מן התורה ולא מהלכות מדינה.
Einam ochlim lo min HaTorah v'lo me'hilchos Medina. How do you know
that's when? Because that's what it said. Let's look. It says, okay,
ושמואל אמר לא שנו אלא שומר גיתות וערימות, V'Shmuel amar lo shanu
ela shomer gitos v'arimos, אבל right,
which is here, that's when it's מהלכות מדינה. Me'hilchos Medina. אבל שומר
גינות ופרדסים, Aval shomer ginos u'pardesim, but if you're here and it's
still growing and if you're before the right time, so אינם אוכלים
לא מן התורה ולא מהלכות מדינה. Einam ochlim lo min HaTorah v'lo
me'hilchos Medina. קסבר משמר לאו כעושה מעשה דמי. Kasvar mishmar lav k'oseh
ma'aseh dami.
Watching is not like you're doing a מעשה, ma'aseh, so even though
it's the right time, you're not actually doing a labor with the
thing, so you're only eating it מהלכות מדינה. mehilchos medinah. Okay. מתיב
רב אחא בר רב הונא. Masiv Rav Acha bar Rav Huna. So
רב אחא בר רב הונא Rav Acha bar Rav Huna asked: השומר
את הפרה מטמא בגדים. Ha-shomer es ha-parah mitameh begadim.
If somebody is watching the פרה parah from the time it's שחט
shechted until it's turned into ashes, then that's like doing a labor
with the פרה parah and you and and it makes your clothes
impure. So that sounds like watching is considered a type of an
engagement with the thing itself. Of course, one could imagine there would
be different standards, but okay. ואי אמרת משמר לאו כעושה מעשה דמי,
V'ee amart mishmar lav k'oseh ma'aseh dami, if you're like שמואל Shmuel
and you say watching is not like you're doing a type of
an action with the thing... itself, a labor with the thing
itself, אמאי מטמא בגדים, amai mitamei begadim, why do your clothes become
טמא? tamei? אמר רבא בר עולא, Amar Rava bar Ulla, גזירה שמא
יזיז באיבר, gezeirah shema yaziz ba'evar, it's only rabbinic. Biblically you're not
really doing a labor with an עצי פרה אדומה atzei parah adumah
which would make your clothes טמא, tamei, but we're concerned that if
you're watching this dead cow whatever you might come to move it
and then you really would be טמא. tamei. Okay, I'm thinking it's
sort of like babysitting, right? If you're babysitting an infant, that that
is like כעושה מעשה דמי. k'oseh ma'aseh dami. That that really then
that really is like a מלאכה. melachah. It's constant ongoing engagement. If
you're if you're babysitting kids who are already asleep when you show
up to be the babysitter, that's not כעושה מעשה דמי. k'oseh ma'aseh
dami. So it sort of sometimes depends exactly the level of the
engagement. Okay, anyway, let's take a look. מתיב רב כהנא. Metiv Rav
Kahana. רב כהנא Rav Kahana says, המשמר ארבעה וחמישה מצפואות, hamishamer arba'ah
v'chamisha mitzpa'ot, if you are watching four or five like sort of
gardens of gourds,
cucumbers, right? קישואים kishu'im are cucumbers? Cucumbers. Cucumber gardens. Okay, הרי זה
לא ימלא כריסו מאחד מהם. harei zeh lo yimale keriso me'echad meihem.
So you're watching four or five cucumber gardens for different owners. Don't
go ahead and fill yourself when you're entitled to eat from one
of them. That's not fair to the other owners. I mean that's
not fair to that owner, excuse me. אלא מכל אחד ואחד אוכל
לפי חשבון. Ela mikol echad v'echad ochel lefi cheshbon. You try to
sort of distribute your eating between the different gardens. Okay, but anyway
the point is you're a שומר shomer and you're watching them while
they are still growing from the ground. You're eating while it's still
growing from the ground, which is רב Rav that you're entitled to
eat while it's still growing from the ground, even though you're only
watching. So the גמרא Gemara says, אביי אמרת דמשמר לאו כעושה מעשה
דמי, Abaye amart d'mishamar lav k'oseh ma'aseh dami, if you say like
שמואל Shmuel that watching it's not like you're doing an action, so
אמאי אוכל, amai ochel, why can you eat according to this? Right?
It's according to שמואל Shmuel you shouldn't be able to eat while
it's growing from the ground. אמר רב שימי בר אשי באקורי
שנו. Amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi b'akurei shanu. No no, we're talking
that the vegetable that the cucumbers have been pulled out from the
ground. So it's so therefore that's why you're allowed to eat according
to שמואל. Shmuel. It's already תלוש. talush. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara,
says, one minute. באקורי והלא לא נגמרה מלאכתן למעשר? B'akurei v'halo lo
nigmerah melachtan l'ma'aser?
As soon as you pull them out of the ground, what else
is left to do with cucumbers? They are חייב במעשר. chayav b'ma'aser.
So you're also not allowed to eat. But it says no, שלא
ניטלו פיקסא שלהם. shelo nitlu piksa shelahem. The the
like the blossom has not been removed and therefore it's not נגמר
מלאכה. nigmar melachah. So according to שמואל Shmuel we're talking about again
you're in this case. It's been harvested but it's not yet נגמר
מלאכה. nigmar melachah. And that's why according to שמואל Shmuel you're entitled
to eat מהלכות מדינה. mehilchos medinah You're not really doing a labor
with it, but מהלכות מדינה mehilchos medinah. you're allowed to. Okay? But
we took but as opposed to the simple sense of that which
was referring to even while it was still growing. Okay, now. אמר
רב אשי כוותיה דשמואל מסתברא, Amar Rav Ashi k'voseh d'Shmuel mistavra, it
makes sense like שמואל, Shmuel, דתנן, detnan, we learned in the משנה,
Mishna ואלו אוכלין מן התורה. v'eilu ochlin min haTorah. The following people
are entitled מן התורה. min haTorah, From this is the first משנה
Mishna that we dealt with with the right of a worker to
eat. The following people are allowed to eat from the תורה: Torah,
העושה במחובר לקרקע בשעת גמר מלאכה. ha'oseh b'mechubar l'karka b'sha'at gmar melachah.
If you do it when it's attached and at the time of
harvesting. ובתלוש ubetalush and it said when it's when it's cut then
it's you can do it until the עד שלא נגמרה מלאכתו למעשר.
ad shelo nigmerah melachto l'ma'aser. Now since it said these eat מן
התורה, min haTorah, מכלל michlal that infers דאיכא דלא קא אכיל מן
התורה אלא מהלכות מדינה. d'ika d'lo ka achil min haTorah ela mehilchos
medinah. That it didn't just say these are entitled to eat. It
says these are entitled to eat מן התורה, min haTorah, which means
that there are some that don't fit that criteria, that don't eat
מן התורה, min haTorah, but eat מהלכות מדינה. Okay, eat from this
practice of the country. אימא סיפא, eima seifa, look at the end
of that משנה. Mishna ואלו שאינם אוכלים, v'eilu she'einam ochlim, the following
don't eat. And it says who doesn't eat? When you're dealing with
something that is תלוש talush and it is I'm sorry well let
me actually remind myself exactly what it says. It says the following
don't eat. Who don't eat? It says ואלו שאינם אוכלין מחובר לקרקע,
v'eilu she'einam ochlim mechubar l'karka, מחובר לקרקע בשעה שאין גמר מלאכה, mechubar
l'karka b'sha'ah she'ein gmar melachah,
when it's attached and it's not גמר מלאכה, and ובתלוש ubetalush after
the נגמרה מלאכתו. nigmerah melachto. Okay, so let's see the gap here.
Okay, it says the following eat eat from the תורה, Torah right?
Okay, and it basically said מחובר mechubar when it's being harvested, right?
בשעת, b'sha'at, right?
And תלוש, talush,
okay, until גמר מלאכה. Okay,
now that says eat from the תורה. Then it says the following
don't eat, which means don't eat at all. And it says מחובר
mechubar
before harvesting,
before harvest,
and תלוש talush
after גמר מלאכה. Okay, now. Here's the problem. Where do you shoehorn
in הלכות halachot. מדינה in here? Because the דיוק diyuk is going
to be the following. These don't eat מן התורה, min haTorah, but
there are but there will still be some scenario okay where you'll
where it won't be this where these do, excuse me, eat מן
התורה, but there'll be some scenario that isn't this that you'll eat
m... הלכות halachot. מדינה *Hilchos Medina*. And then it says these don't
eat which presumably mean don't eat at all. Okay, so where are
you going to get into הלכות מדינה *Hilchos Medina*? This seems to
be like covering the entire range of activity. When it's מחובר *mechubar*
and it's not the שעת *shas*... Ah but that says don't eat
at all. So that's what this is the דיוק *diyuk*. Here it
says מחובר *mechubar* harvested it's מן התורה *min hatorah* and then it
says
before harvest...
right that's this, it's not at all.
So there is no space here, this is harvested and before harvest,
there's no space here where you can eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina*.
Right? Now how about this? תלוש *Talush* it says until גמר מלאכה
*gmar melacha* and not at all is after גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha*.
So there's no space here between these two moments where you can
eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina*. Where can you eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos
medina*? So שמואל *Shmuel* says I've got an answer. My answer is
that you can eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina*, okay, until... when it's
until גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha* but you're not real doing real מלאכה
*melacha*. You're just watching it, okay? That's when. There's... it's true, there's
no gap here but even so you can... you can still eat
מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina* when you're in this space and it's... and
but you're not doing real מלאכה *melacha*, you're just watching. That at
least can fit in, okay? But when you do real מלאכה *melacha*
until here you eat מן התורה *min hatorah*, when it's not real
מלאכה *melacha* whatever. But according to רב *Rav*, רב *Rav* says that
משמר *mishamer* is real מלאכה *melacha* and he says you're entitled to
eat here cause you're... cause you're entitled to eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos
medina* before harvest. But that doesn't fit here cause this says before
harvest you don't eat at all.
Right? So since this entirely covers the entire scope, harvested before harvest,
until גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha* after גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha*, there's no
time period where you're allowed to eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina*. That
goes against רב *Rav*. רב *Rav* says there's a time period you're
allowed to eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina* when you do real מלאכה
*melacha* prior to harvest. But what שמואל *Shmuel* says it does work
for me because I would say the when you're allowed to eat
מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina* is not at a certain time period, it's
when you're doing something at the right time period, the right time
period but you're just doing something that's not a real מלאכה *melacha*,
you're only watching the garden. Okay? Is that pretty clear? Let's see
how it's... let's see it's in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אמר רב
אשי *Amar Rav Ashi* כוותיה דשמואל מסתברא *k'vassay deShmuel mistavra*. תנן *Tnan*
ואלו אוכלין מן התורה *ve'elu ochlin min hatorah* עושה במחובר לקרקע בשעת
גמר מלאכה ובתלוש וכו׳ *oseh bimchubar lekarka besha'as gmar melacha ubetalush etcetera*.
מכלל דאיכא דלא אכלי מן התורה מהלכות מדינה *Michlal de'ika d'lo ochlin
min hatorah mihilchos medina*. The fact that it says מן התורה *min
hatorah* suggests that somebody is going to eat in some type of
a scenario that's מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina*. אימא סיפא *Eima seifa* look
at the end ואלו שאינם אוכלין *ve'elu she'einam ochlin*. The following don't
eat at all. מאי mai, אין אוכלין *Mai ein ochlin*? אילימא שאין
אוכלין מן התורה אלא מהלכות מדינה *Ileiima she'ein ochlin min hatorah ella
mihilchos medina* they don't eat from the Torah but they do eat
מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina* היינו רישא *hainu reisha*. We already said in
the רישא *reisha* that if you're not in this category, something not
in this category will eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina*. So saying 'not
you don't eat' means you don't eat at all. אלא לאו שאין
אוכלין לא מן התורה ולא מהלכות מדינה *Ella lav she'ein ochlin lo
min hatorah velo mihilchos medina*. ומני *U'many* when do you not eat
from either? עושה במחובר לקרקע בשעה שאין גמר מלאכה *Oseh bimchubar lekarka
besha'as she'ein gmar melacha* when you are doing it before גמר מלאכה
*gmar melacha*. And that's even... that's even if you're doing real מלאכה
*melacha* too early you wouldn't eat. כל שכן *Kol sheken* שומר shomer
גנות ופרדסין *shomer ganos upardaysin* and certainly if you're only watching it.
So basically since this means not at all, it's against רב *Rav*,
cause this says before harvest even real מלאכה *melacha* you don't eat
at all. So the only thing we're left with is שמואל *Shmuel*
who שמואל *Shmuel* says the time you eat מהלכות מדינה *mihilchos medina*
is when it's at a time that you normally would be entitled
to eat, this period of time, but you're doing it in a
way that's not a real מלאכה *melacha*, you're only watching the garden.
Yes? Do you have anything else to say about this category of
הלכות מדינה *hilchos medina* because first of all by calling it הלכות
מדינה *hilchos medina* it becomes a halakhic category. Yeah, I mean that's
funny the phrase הלכות *hilchos*. Like civil marriage, possibly, like it's another...
No, I mean this picks up on an earlier משנה Mishna. *mishna*
that says הכל כמנהג המדינה *hakol k'minhag hamedina* when you're certainly dealing
with
contractual obligations that those get implicitly shaped by the norms of the...
of business practices, right, etc. But it is funny the word הלכות
*hilchos* although somebody told me that הלכה *halakha* was actually I don't
know it's some type of... I was trying to remember somebody told
me it was some type
of... like people think it's derived from the word like you know
the Hebrew word הליכה *halicha* to go but apparently it's derived... I...
I don't want to say this without double checking but I heard
it was derived from maybe a Persian word or something that more
had more to do with stuff like law or custom or practice.
I don't know, something like that. Yeah. Anyway now we move on.
That was the end of the worker's rights to eat and now
and for the life of me I've never understood why a new
פרק *perek* does not begin here. It says the last two משניות
*mishnayot* of this... of the seventh פרק *perek* begin the new topic
of שומרים shomrim *shomrim*. So let's take a look. Okay and this
is like the משנה Mishna *mishna* that frames the basic responsibilities of
שומרים shomrim. *shomrim*. Brand new topic. ארבעה שומרים arba'ah shomrim? הן *Arba
shomrim hein*. There are four שומרים shomrim, *shomrim*. but he is not
being paid to watch, he gets all the benefit. שומר חנם shomer
chinam, והשואל Ve'hashoel נושא שכר והשוכר. nosei sachar ve'hasocher The one who
acts for free, the borrower, who's not a שומר shomer, but it
means there are four categories of liability, okay, because he's handling somebody
else's object, but he is not being paid to watch, he gets
all the benefit.
נושא שכר, Nosei sachar, somebody who is being paid to watch, so
really the two types of שומרים shomrim. are free, somebody who's watching
for free and somebody who's being paid to watch. והשוכר, Ve'hasocher, and
somebody who's renting it who also has the object of somebody else's,
and it's a type of an exchange. He gets use and he
pays for it. Now, שומר חנם, shomer chinam somebody who's watching it
is only giving who's only doing something for free for the owner,
his liability is the least. Okay, נשבע על הכל, nishba al hakol,
anything that happens he swears he wasn't negligent and he's exempt, as
long as he wasn't negligent. והשואל who's only getting and not giving,
he's only getting the use of the object, so he has the
highest liability. משלם את הכל. Meshalem et hakol. So he pays if
anything goes wrong even if it's an אונס, ones, even if it's
something that could completely, you know, not preventable, completely, yeah. ונושא שכר
והשוכר Ve'nosei sachar ve'hasocher now those two are very similar because they're
an exchange. Either I'm watching it for you and you're paying me
for my service of watching, or I'm renting it from you and
I'm paying you for your right to use. So in those two,
they're at a middle level of obligation. נשבע על השבורה ועל השבויה
ועל המתה, Nishba al hashvura ve'al hashvuya ve'al amaysa, they swear to
not that if there was something that was an אונס, ones, something
that was could not have been prevented, you know, and it was
no negligence, they swear that that's what happened and they're exempt. So
they're exempt if it was a complete אונס. ones. ומשלם את האבידה
ואת הגניבה. Umeshalem et ha'aveida ve'at hagneiva. If it's something that was
not gross negligence, but had they done a really, you know, excellent
job of watching it it wouldn't have happened like gotten lost and
gotten stolen, those types of cases they actually have to pay. So
they pay for שומר חנם shomer chinam. only pays for full negligence,
נושא שכר noseh sachar, והשוכר pays for anytime that it's not real
אונס, ones, you know, not a total accident and uncontrollable, and a
שואל shoel even pays for אונס. ones. Now
the גמרא Gemara immediately gets into the question about about what is
the logic of the שוכר socher because the שומר שכר shomer sachar
makes a lot of sense. You're watching for me and you're being
paid to watch. So that I'm paying you specifically to do the
job of watching heightens your level of responsibility. But if you're a
שוכר, socher, if you're just renting it, it's true you have my
object, it's true it was somewhat of an equal exchange, but fundamentally
this is here to help you, you know, to help you, like
you needed to borrow this, I mean I'm also making money off
of it, okay, but it's not like your direct responsibility to the
object is to watch it. So even though it's similar to a
שומר שכר shomer sachar that there's an exchange going on here, okay,
you could reasonably understand that my liability would be less. I'm only
incidentally a שומר, shomer, I'm primarily a borrower and a user of
it. Okay, so that's the question in the גמרא: Gemara. what is
the obligation of a שוכר? socher? מאן תנא ארבעה שומרים, Man tana
arba'ah shomrim, who's the author of our
משנה? Mishna. אמר רב נחמן אמר בר אבוה רבי מאיר היא, Amar
Rav Nachman amar Bar Abbuha Rabbi Meir hi, it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava l'Rav Nachman, so
רבא Rava said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, מי איכא דליתי ארבעה
שומרים, mi ikka d'laytei arba'ah shomrim, who doesn't hold of this משנה
Mishna of
ארבעה שומרים? אמר ליה Amar lei no, everybody holds that there are
four types of שומרים. אמר ליה Amar lei no no, הכי קאמינא
לך, hachi ka'amina lach, this is what I mean. מאן תנא שוכר
כנושא שכר, Man tana socher k'nosei sachar, who is the תנא Tana
who holds like the categorization of this משנה Mishna, that you put
the שוכר socher in the category of the שומר שכר, shomer sachar,
of the one who is being paid to watch? רבי מאיר היא,
Rabbi Meir hi, that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and that's basically the
way we פוסקים. pasken. So the גמרא Gemara says wait, why would
you say such a thing? ורבי מאיר איפכא שמעינא ליה, Ve'Rabbi Meir
ipcha shamina lei, we have a ברייתא braita that has רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir saying the exact opposite. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita,
שוכר כיצד משלם, socher keitzad meshalem, how does a שוכר socher pay?
רבי מאיר אומר כשומר חנם, Rabbi Meir omer k'shomer chinam, actually you're
only liable like a שומר חנם. shomer chinam Your job of watching
is only incidental to your relationship to this object and therefore you
have the lowest level of responsibility. רבי יהודה אומר כשומר שכר, Rabbi
Yehuda omer k'shomer sachar, no you're like a שומר שכר, shomer sachar,
since there's an exchange here it's not all one direction, you have
a middle level of responsibility. So anyway our משנה Mishnah. seems to
be רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, of course the problem is that a
סתם משנה stam Mishna is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So the גמרא
Gemara says רבה בר אבוה איפכא קתני, Rabba Bar Abbuha ipcha katani,
his ברייתא braita has it reversed, he's got רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
saying a שוכר socher is like a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, which
is consistent with our משנה. אי הכי ארבעה שלשה נינהו? I hachi
arba'ah, shlosha ninhu? Okay, says the גמרא, Gemara but anyway you categorize
it, it's not four different הלכות, it's only three different הלכות. Four
different roles but three different הלכות. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק ארבעה שומרים, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak arba'ah
shomrim, there are four people that are שומרים, now again doesn't mean
you're hired to be a שומר, shomer but somebody else's object is
under your is in your property that's under your control, you are
de facto watching somebody else's object. Okay, so there are four types
of people that are wat... either de facto or they've been hired
to do it watching
somebody else's object. ודיניהם שלשה, V'dinehem shlosha, and their categories only negligence,
anything other than אונס, ones, and even אונס. ones. Okay
now okay, and we this משנה assumes that a שוכר socher is
like a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Good, that's just פשט pshat in
the משנה. Now נושא שכר, noseh sachar right. נושא שכר is a
way of saying שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara is going to have some interesting cases. And now we're going
to get to this question about what is the right level of
watching that is considered to be, you know, negligence or not negligence
or whatever, or even good for a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. ההוא
רעיא דהוה קא רעי חיוותא אגודא דנהר פפא. Hahu raya d'hava ka
rai chivata aguda d'nahar pappa. So there was a certain shepherd who
was watching, you know, the animals by the banks of the river
Pappa, of the, of נהר פפא. Nahar Pappa. שריג חד מינייהו ונפל
למיא. Sharig chad mineihu v'nafal l'maya. One of them slipped and fell
into the water. אתא לקמיה דרבה, Ata l'kamei d'Rabba, the case came
to Rabba. Now if he's a shepherd, he is a שומר שכר,
shomer sachar, he's being paid. Okay, so it came to Rabba. Rabba
said ופטריה, ufatrieh, Rabba exempted him. It's an
אונס. ones. אמר מאי הוה ליה למעבד, Amar mai hava lei l'maavad,
what could he have done? Even if he had been trying super
careful, what are you supposed to do? You're supposed to hold on
to every sheep as it's grazing? I mean, I don't know, maybe
you could tape off like a yellow line, like they have at
the subway, like a raised line right near the edge of the
river. But you know, how, even if you were doing everything you
could do, you know, that could have been prevented. נטרי כדנטרי אינשי,
Natri k'dnatri inshi, he watched it like normal people watched it. Now
that is not what I just said a minute ago. A minute
ago I said, or a second ago I said, he couldn't have
prevented it no matter how hard he tried. That's not what Rabba
said. Rabba said he did the normal watching. Now that's really interesting,
right? When you say a שומר שכר shomer sachar is חייב chayav
because, you know, it could have been prevented, based on what standard
could have been prevented? Could have been prevented based on the standard
of theoretically there are things you could have done if you were
to have, you know, to have done 110% you would have been
able to prevent it? Or do we say, no, actually you're חייב
chayav if, if you did everything that was normal to be done,
then anything that happens beyond that is considered not preventable. Your only
expectation is to do, you know, the sort of what is normally
done in terms of watching this, which is really funny, then what's
the difference between that and between פשיעה, pshia, negligence? Right, maybe there's
a different standard for like paid watchers than there are for שומרי
חינם. shomrei chinam. Correct. Right. But then the difference doesn't become this
theoretical question of was it an אונס ones or not, but just
like what is the normal standard for somebody who's watching it for
free and what is the normal standard for somebody who's being paid?
But this is a very powerful and radical statement by Rabba, that
to determine that you're exempt as long as you've done what is
sort of the normal way in which, you know, it's accepted, right?
There's no objective standard. What if in different, you know, different locales
they have different levels of accepted responsibility? It's all a function of
that. All right. And if some, and I don't understand, and if
some place it was understood that a שומר חינם shomer chinam and
a שומר שכר shomer sachar watch to the same degree, like would
that mean that they have the same level of liability? You know,
like, or maybe it's the opposite. Maybe נטרי אינשי natri inshi defines
the level for a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Maybe a שומר חינם
shomer chinam even if you do less than נטרי אינשי natri inshi
you're exempt until you're grossly negligent, until you do like radically less,
right? Maybe נטרי אינשי, natri inshi, maybe there aren't different levels for
שומר חינם shomer chinam and שומר שכר. shomer sachar. There's a normal
level that, you know, owners or, you know, normal responsible people do.
If you're a שומר שכר shomer sachar you do below that, you're
חייב. chayav. If you're a שומר חינם shomer chinam only if you
do enormously below that you're חייב. chayav. Otherwise it's not considered gross
negligence. So it's a very real, you know, radical idea that Rabba
puts out here, but he sort of says you've got to measure
it through a subjective standard, or you know, a contextual standard, not
through some objective reality could it have been prevented? Yes. Is the
משנה in contradiction to what we learned a פרק or two ago
about the workers who made a mistake and? That wasn't a משנה,
that was a גמרא. Gemara And that גמרא Gemara was talking about
לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishurat hadin, so that was a different issue.
Okay, and that had to do also with whether tripping is tripping
an אונס, ones, is tripping כעין אבידה, k'ein aveidah, so that's also
a question how do you measure the degree of negligence. We could
perhaps frame it as maybe there's,
there's an objective standard of פשיעה pshia and there's an objective standard
of אונס ones and then maybe there's some gray area between them
which can then be contractually negotiated which would then be why it
depends on נטרי אינשי, natri inshi, who's watching.
Right, right, meaning that's what I was saying, meaning נטרי אינשי natri
inshi determines the level for a
שומר שכר. shomer sachar. But there could still be objective levels of
פשיעה, pshia, or what you're saying is שומר חינם shomer chinam is
not two degrees removed from נטרי אינשי, natri inshi, שומר חינם shomer
chinam is an objective... Right, that's possible, right. That there's an objective
פשיעה, pshia, gross negligence of שומר חינם, shomer chinam, there's an objective
אונס, ones, and anything in between, right, the level is based on
נטרי אינשי. natri inshi. That's maybe a helpful way of framing it.
Yes. And I know this is קציצה, ketzitza, right?
And I know this is all implicit, although it's... Right, right. אמר
ליה אביי אלא מעתה, Amar lei Abaye ela meata, if that's true,
now אביי Abaye tries to push רבא Rava in a different direction,
but he says if everything is based on the norms, then how
about the following scenario? Now רבא Rava was talking about the norms
of degree of watching. אביי Abaye is going to be talking about
times of watching.
אמר ליה אביי אלא מעתה עאל למתא בעידנא דעיילי אינשי. Amar lei
Abaye ela meata aal l'mata b'idna d'ayli inshi. Let's say you left
the sheep and you went into the city because it was lunchtime,
and that's the practice, shepherds go into the city for lunchtime, הכי
נמי דפטור hachi nami d'fatur and then something happened? Or would you
be exempt? I mean, you know, you could have just stayed there
and had your lunch there, okay, but this is the practice, everybody
goes into the town for lunch. So אמר ליה אין amar lei
in yeah, you'd be exempt. Right, which is like really shocking, like
what שמירה shmira did he do at that time? So this is
even saying not that this constitutes sufficient שמירה shmira but that the
your the time period when you're expected to be when you're in
your role as a שומר shomer is determined by the norms. And
if there's a norms that this is your lunch break and this
is your coffee break, then even though I wasn't being a שומר
shomer at all, you know, I was not obligated to be שומר
shomer. during that time.
Dunkin' Donuts is ten minutes, right, Corner Cafe is an hour and
a half. Well, that
all depends on what the norms are. So גנבא פורצתא בעידנא דגנו
אינשי ganba purtzta be'idna deganu inshi let's say you didn't go into
the town, let's say you took a little, you know, three afternoon,
siesta, 3:00 PM siesta, and that's when people do it. If it's
normal for for shepherds to take five-minute naps and that's accepted, הכי
נמי דפטור hachi nami depatur would you be exempt? אמר ליה אין
amar lei in yes. So it's really crazy, I mean, you know,
שומר שכר shomer sachar you think is חייב chayav for everything except
אונס. ones. And here it's no, a שומר שכר'ס shomer sachar's חיוב
chiyuv is based on, you know, the norms of the, you know,
and the standards. And therefore that determines the level of care, that
determines the time of care, and if the norms are you're allowed
to take a break, then that's
accepted, until until you do something to violate the norm, you are,
you know, you are still you are you are exempt as a
שומר שכר. shomer sachar. I mean it's a very nice rule for
the שומרים. Okay, and you can sort of understand it, like you're
paying me like you could you understand, meaning, it's it's hard to
understand given that we're always taught that a שומר שכר shomer sachar
is חייב chayav for anything short of אונס. ones. It's reasonable to
understand if you were just to start with a blank slate and
you said, you paid somebody to watch. What should we assume is
the level of care? So the level of care is how do
normal people who are paid to watch things, what's their normal level
of care, right? So that would be very reasonable, okay, it's just
not reasonable based on what we're normally taught. All right, so now
the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר ליה amar lei okay, איתיביה. eitivei. אלו הן אונסין ששומר שכר
פטור עליהן כגון ותפול שבא ותקחם ואת הנערים הכו לפי חרב. elu
hen onsin sheshomer sachar patur aleihen kagon vatipol sheva vatikachem ve'et hanearim
hiku lefi charev. So like when there's when there's like these troops
like descended, you know, these army troops like descended and and and
and smote the the the the lads and took all of the
booty here of איוב Iyov or whatever, all of his property, okay.
So basically you have invading troops. That's an אונס. ones. Okay, that's
a little bit more of an אונס ones than just going in
for your normal your afternoon nap. So אמר ליה amar lei so
obviously if any if that's what's an אונס, ones, things that are
less than that are not an אונס. ones. אמר ליה amar lei
התם בחזני מתא. hatam bechazanei mata. No, no, no, that's talking about
the people that are watch the city, the city guards. Those people
don't get any breaks. Those people have to always be at the
top of their game. איתיביה eitivei okay, I'll ask you another question.
עד מתי שומר שכר חייב לשמור עד כדי מיעקב הייתי ביום אכלני
חרב וקרח בלילה. ad matai shomer sachar chayav lishmor ad kedei mi'Yaakov
hayiti bayom achalani chorev vekerach balaila.
You know, I was there by the hot sun of the day
and the cold of the night. So you see, it's not like
I'm allowed to go ahead and take a little nap and take
a little break and to go into the city or whatever. So
clearly it's not some subjective norm. It's based on an objective high
standard. אמר ליה amar lei התם נמי בחזני מתא. hatam nami bechazanei
mata. No, there too, that's just a standard for city guard city
watchers, for the guards of the city. אמר ליה amar lei אטו
יעקב אבינו חזן מתא הוה? atu Yaakov Avinu chazan mata hava? I
don't understand, you think יעקב אבינו Yaakov Avinu was a guard of
a city? That he was he was a shepherd. Clearly we're talking
about the level for shepherds. No, so the גמרא Gemara says no.
דאמר ליה ללבן de'amar lei le'Lavan is true, he was only a
shepherd and therefore he could have watched at a much lower level.
But he said to לבן Lavan נטרתי לך נטירותא יתירתא. natarti lach
netiruta yetirata. You should know לבן, Lavan, I did an extra job
for you. I watched it so well כחזני מתא kechazanei mata as
I would have as if I'd been a city guard. Now of
course this question isn't in the פסוקים pesukim in the תורה, in
the פסוקים pesukim in the תורה sure, that's what it sounds like,
that יעקב Yaakov is saying I did 110 percent, I did much
more than I should have done. The problem is that the ברייתא
braita says that that's the standard for שומר. shomer So now what
we have to say is that it doesn't mean it's the standard
for shepherds, it means it's the standard for, you know, city guards.
All right. איתיביה eitivei it doesn't sound like it. Obviously all of
the tannaitic material sounds like it's against
רבא. Rava. איתיביה eitivei רועה שהיה רועה והניח עדרו ובא לעיר ובא
זאב וטרף
ובא ארי וטרף אין אומרים או עומדים אילו היה שם היה מציל.
ro'eh shehaya ro'eh vehiniach edro uva la'ir uva ze'ev vetaraf uva ari
vetaraf ein omrim o omdim ilu haya sham haya matzil.
You don't say oh, clearly he's חייב chayav because if he had
stayed with the flock he would have saved them. You don't just
assume that he could have saved them had he been with the
flock. אלא אומדין אותו ela omdin oto you try to assess the
situation.
אם יכול להציל חייב ואם לאו פטור. im yachol lehatzil chayav ve'im
lav patur. The answer is yes, he's חייב chayav for having abandoned
them because then he's negligent and his leaving is liable. Okay. אם
לאו, Im lav, if you say even had he been there, he
couldn't have saved them, פטור, patur, he's exempt. Okay, and the תחילתו
בפשיעה t'chilato bipshiah we'll get to that. Okay, but anyway but the
Gemara says it sounds though like even though he took his break
presumably at a normal time, that's not enough to exempt him. Right?
You still say he should have been there. מאי לאו דעביד בעידנא
דעיילי אינשי? Mai lav d'avid b'idna d'ayli inshi? It sounds like presumably
he went for a normal break and he's still not exempt? You
say if he would have been there and could have saved it,
he's חייב? chayav? ומשני לא, לא, דעביד בעידנא דלא עיילי אינשי. Umeshani
lo, lo, d'avid b'idna d'lo ayli inshi. He took his coffee break
at the not normal time. אי הכי אמאי פטור? Ei hachi amai
patur? So now the Gemara says fine, so what do you want
to say? You want to read this that he basically was negligent
when he left? If he was negligent when he left, why do
we care had he... could he have saved them or could he
not have saved them had he been there? If it started with
negligence, he left when he shouldn't have
left, תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס חייב. t'chilato bipshiah v'sofo b'ones chayav. Then
he should be חייב chayav even if it even if he couldn't
have saved them, because his first act of leaving was an act
of אונס ones and פשיעה, pshiah, and פשיעה pshiah that ends with
אונס ones you're חייב. chayav. I had the same question on Abaye.
Yeah, so Tosafot deals with that. Okay. So Gemara says it says
before it would have been like at the level of גניבה ואבידה,
gneivah v'aveidah, here it's only level of פשיעה. pshiah. Anyway, okay. דשמע
קול אריה ובא. D'shama kol aryeh v'ava. Okay, so he left, but
he left not at the time that was a break when he
would have been totally פטור patur according to Rava, but he wasn't
also פושע poshea when he left. Why did he leave? Because he
heard a lion's roaring, and what he decided is, a lion is
roaring, this is my time to go into the bar! As opposed
to this is my time to start doing something to protect the
flock. Okay, but the Gemara says okay, but nevertheless if he was
really an אונס ones by running to town, it's like make up
your mind. If he was a פושע poshea by running to town
when he heard the lion, same question, why is he ever פטור?
patur? If it was an אונס ones when he ran to town,
then why is he חייב chayav because you say if he had
been there he could have saved this? אי הכי אומדין אותו? Ei
hachi omdin oto? But so why do you say, "Oh, had he
been there if he could have saved it, he would have whatever"?
מאי הוה ליה למיעבד? Mai hava lei lemievad? What did he do
wrong? He ran to town when he heard a lion. So Gemara
says no, because a good shepherd doesn't run to town as soon
as you hear a lion.
הוה ליה לקדומי ברועי ובמקלות. Hava lei l'kadumi b'roei u'b'maklot. No, what
he should have done is if he heard the lion, he should
have gotten all the shepherds together and he should have gotten all
their sticks and whatever and started organizing a, you know, something to
protect the animals. אי הכי מאי איריא שומר שכר? Ei hachi mai
irya shomer sachar? Okay, so therefore so what have we said? He
ran to town when he heard the lion. So was he an
אונס ones or was he a, you know,
or was he a פושע, poshea, was he חייב? chayav? So basically
says well look, you assess. If it were something that he could
have protected against, had he been there he could have protected it,
then he was negligent for leaving, right? Then he should have raised
up the shepherds and protected it. So his leaving was negligent. If
had he been there he couldn't have protected it, then again I
don't know how he knew that but maybe there was still a
degree of negligence, but then at least he wasn't grossly negligent for
leaving because it wasn't like he just סתם stam left, he actually
was afraid or whatever, it wasn't gross negligence. And therefore if he
couldn't have protected it, had even had he been there, so he's
exempt. Had he been there he would have protected it, it didn't
start with a gross act of פשיעה, pshiah, he'd be exempt. Okay,
so that's what we have. He ran because of the lion. It
was a certain degree of fault because he should have done something
to protect the animals, but it wasn't gross negligence. And therefore to
determine if he's חייב chayav we say, if he had been there
he could have protected it, he's חייב. chayav. If he had been
there he couldn't have protected it, then he's exempt and it wasn't
really תחילתו בפשיעה. t'chilato bipshiah. So now the Gemara says if that's
true, אי הכי מאי איריא שומר שכר? ei hachi mai irya shomer
sachar? אפילו שומר חנם נמי? Afilu shomer chinam nami? One minute, then
why is the liability here only for a שומר שכר? shomer sachar?
Even a שומר חנם shomer chinam should have protected an animal if
you heard a... if you heard lion coming. דהא mar הוא דאמר,
you're the one who says, שומר חנם שהיה לו לקדם ברועים ובמקלות,
shomer chinam shehayah lo l'kadem b'roim u'b'maklot, if a שומר חנם shomer
chinam could have sort of, you know, and got ahead and protect
and sort of, you know, protect against the attack by getting all
the shepherds
together, ולא קידם חייב, v'lo kidem chayav, and he didn't he's חייב.
chayav. So therefore basically, you know, it wouldn't matter שומר חנם shomer
chinam or שומר שכר shomer sachar here, the way you're describing the
case it's the same issue. So the
Gemara says no, שומר חנם בחנם שומר שכר בשכר. shomer chinam b'chinam
shomer sachar b'sachar. A שומר חנם shomer chinam does not... does not
have to spend any money or to try to protect the animals.
A שומר שכר shomer sachar who's being paid for his job,
he has to actually hire people when he hears a lion coming
and spend money in order to protect the animals. So now the
Gemara says ועד כמה? v'ad kamah? So let's sort of finish up
this train of thought and then we'll go back and explain the
Braitah. How much money does he have to spend to hire people
to protect the animals, a שומר שכר? shomer sachar? עד כדי דמיהן,
ad k'dei d'meihen, until the full value of the flock. So now
the Gemara says one minute, והיכן מצינו בשומר שכר שחייב באונס? v'heichan
matzinu b'shomer sachar shechayav b'ones? Since I, the שומר שכר, shomer sachar,
have to spend out-of-pocket money to hire protectors, then this is an
אונס, ones, the lion came it's an אונס, ones, the presence of
the lion coming meaning whether the lion attacks or not, okay, so
and why am I losing money for? something that's an אונס. ones.
The coming of the lion is an אונס, ones, right, and therefore,
and all of a sudden you tell me I have to spend
my own money? But I'm a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, I'm not
חייב chayav to lose money for an אונס. ones. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, דהדר שקיל דמי מבעל הבית. dahadar shakil damei miba'al
habayit. No, no, no, you just have to front the money. You're
going to get reimbursed by the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, which is
interesting. A שומר חינם shomer chinam doesn't even have to front the
money, okay? But as a שומר שכר shomer sachar you have to
front the money and you'll get reimbursed. And there's a certain cap
that's the value of the flock? Yes, of the דמי מניינה demei
minyanah because the owner wouldn't want to spend more than the value
of the flock. But now the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה רב
פפא לאביי אי הכי מאי אהני ליה... amar lei Rav Papa le'Abayei
ei hachi mai ahani lei... מאי אהני
ליה מינה? mai ahani lei minah? So then the גמרא Gemara says
so if the owner is reimbursing him, why does the owner want
him to spend up to the value of the flock? What if
it's if it's going to be maybe a, what do I profit?
Just let it happen, right? Why should he be allowed to spend
the full value of the
flock if I'm going to have to reimburse you, right? What good
does it do me to protect the flock that I now have
to pay their full value for? So it's got the flock and
it will continue to then produce. So that's what
the גמרא says: נפקא מינה לאקושי דחיותא. nafka minah le'akushi dechiyuta. First
of all, to just habituate the animals. I'd rather keep with the
flock I'm used to. אינמי לטירחא יתירתא, einami letircha yetirta, or just
the effort to go ahead and to buy such a flock. It's
not that everything is reducible to its dollar amount, okay? Up to
a so up to its full value I want to protect the
flock. Fine. Now anyway, this is the basic explanation. So we have
this idea where it sounds like going to the city was an
act of
was a certain was not a full negligence, but was not something
you should have done and therefore you're liable if you could have
prevented it. And the גמרא reframes it as you didn't just סתם
stam go to the city. You went to the city because a
lion was coming and therefore the question is that also was a
certain degree of negligence because you should have hired people, but it
wasn't gross negligence. And because it wasn't gross negligence, if it really
was unpreventable, you'll be exempt. If it was preventable, then you'll be
liable. Okay, now the גמרא gets back to this position of רבא
Rava that very much limits the liability based on the norms. So
the גמרא says the
following: רב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא לא סבירא להו הא דרבא.
Rav Chisda verabbah bar Rav Huna lo sevira lehu ha deRava. They
don't they didn't agree with רבא, Rava, okay? That that it's limited
by these norms. דאמרי להכי יהבי לך אגרא, de'amri lehachi yahavi lach
agra, this is why I'm paying you a
fee, לנטור לי נטירותא יתירתא, lintur li netiruta yetirta, that you should
do an extra job of watching, okay? Which by the way, makes
it sound like the norms of נשי אינשי nashi inshi might be
נשי אינשי nashi inshi even שומר חינם. shomer chinam. Because he's saying
I'm paying you a fee that you should do higher than the
norms. So it's all it's not clear to me who defines the
norms, שומר חינם shomer chinam or שומר שכר. shomer sachar. But anyway,
they say when you pay a guy to be a watcher, it's
not enough to do the norms. They have to do an extra
job. Okay, בר אדא סבולא, Bar Adda Sabola, this person, הוה קא
מעבר חיותא אגמלא דנרש. hava ka ma'avar chiyuta agamla deNarash.
He was having the animals go over this bridge of נרש. Narash.
דחפה חדא לחברתה, dachfa chada lechaverta,
one of the animals, a sheep, pushed the other one, ושדייה במיא,
veshadya bemaya,
and it fell into the water. אתא לקמיה דרב פפא, ata likamei
deRav Papa, came to רב פפא, Rav Papa, חייביה, chayvei, he said
you have to pay the owner. You were the shepherd, you have
to pay the owner, you're a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. אמר ליה
מאי הוה לי למעבד, amar lei mai hava li lema'avad, what could
I have done? אמר ליה איבעי לך לאעבורי חדא חדא, amar lei
ibayei lach le'avuri chada chada, you should have had them go single
file, even though that wasn't the practice, okay? So this is a
position against רבא. Rava. Sure, the practice of shepherds is to do
it two at a time. But if you were really doing everything
to make sure nothing would happen, you would have done it one
at a time. So you didn't do less than the standard, but
you did less than could have been done. And this is exactly
the position that argues on רבא. Rava.
It's a slightly different argument, right? It's not what could I have
done to save it once it fell in the water? It's you
didn't do the job. Oh, yeah, that's what I assumed we were
talking about all along, was that what could you have done to
prevent it? To prevent it. Right, right, so I thought it was
like no, no, no, no. No, that was more with the lions,
but not the earlier case. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said
anyway, but this is the position against רבא. Rava. Yes, you did
the norm, but you didn't do everything you could have done. אמר
ליה ידעת בה בבר אחותך דמצי למיעבד
חדא חדא? amar lei yadit bah bevar achvotach dematzi lemiavad chada chada?
Do you know that your sister's son, meaning your co-religionist,
is this really something you expect from your fellow Jew, that we
should spend our time having animals go single file? Like, we got
more important things to do, like, this is an unrealistic expectation! What
normal person makes the animals walk single file? Okay, which is basically
saying it should be limited by norms, it shouldn't be by some
theoretical doing the maximum that's theoretically possible. אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said back to him, כבר שביקנא קמחי דקמחית ולא איכא דאשגח בהו.
kevar shevikna kamchei dekamchit velo ika de'ashgach behu. Yeah,
I've had other people yell at me too. Okay? It doesn't do
you any good, okay? It's very nice, you everybody all you poor
shepherds complaining that I'm being unrealistic? I'm sorry, I'm not hearing your
complaints. You can do a better job. You're being paid, and if
you don't do what is maximally possible, you'll be liable, okay? That's
part of the deal. Right, so he's not changing, he's saying that
might be the norms, but maybe you can go ahead and do
that but then you're gonna pay. Right? The norms, this means as
if there could be a reality that the norms are to do
less, and the norms will remain to do less, except what it
will also remain is that you'll wind up paying. If you want
to not pay, you'll do more than the norms. You'll do what
is maximally possible. Okay, so this was the position against
רבא. Rava. Okay, איבו אפקיד כיתנא בי רניא. Aivo afkid kitna bei
Runya. This person איבו Aivo put some flax by the house of
רניא, Runya, ואתו שבו. ve'atu Shavu. שבו Shavu is the name of
רש"י says of some גנב, ganav, some ליסטין מזויין, listin mezuyan, some
armed
thief. ולסוף הוכר הגנב. Ulesof hucar haganav. In the end the גנב
ganav was found, שבו Shavu was identified. So what's the issue? Everybody
gets paid back. Here's the issue. Does the שומר shomer have to
pay the owner and then he has to work to get reimbursed
from the גנב? ganav? Or does the שומר shomer. get out of
there and the גנב ganav and the owner deal with it? אתו
לקמיה דרב נחמן. Atu lekamei deRav Nachman. They came to רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. חייביה. Chiyvei. He said you pay the owner and then
you go ahead and you deal with the גנב, ganav,
okay? So that's part of your responsibility of a שומר. shomer Now
is he a שומר חנם shomer chinam, or a שומר שכר? shomer
sachar? We'll take a look.
לימא פליגא דרב הונא בר אבין. Leima peliga deRav Huna bar Avin.
Let's say this argues on רב הונא בר אבין. Rav Huna bar
Avin. דשלח רב הונא בר אבין. Deshalach Rav Huna bar Avin. רב
הונא בר אבין Rav Huna bar Avin sent, נגנבה באונס, nigneva be'ones,
if it was stolen by an אונס ones like the guy was
an armed bandit, והוכר הגנב, vehucar haganav, and the גנב ganav was
found. אם שומר חנם הוא, Im shomer chinam hu, if you're a
שומר חנם, shomer chinam, רצה נשבע רצה עושה עמו דין. ratza nishba
ratza oseh imo din. If you're a שומר חנם, shomer chinam you
choose to swear to the owner that you weren't negligent and the
owner gets his money back from the גנב, ganav, or
you pay the owner and you get your money back from the
גנב. ganav. אם שומר שכר הוא, Im shomer sachar hu, עושה עמו
דין ואינו נשבע. oseh imo din ve'eino nishba.
Then you have no choice. Even though it was an אונס ones
and as a שומר שכר shomer sachar you're פטור patur in אונס,
ones, once the גנב ganav is found, you pay the owner and
you get reimbursed. So this is very interesting. You don't just say
it was an אונס, ones, I'm out of here. Being an אונס
ones means you're exempt from losing money, from having to pay out
of pocket, but even though it was an אונס ones and you're
not going to lose out of money, as a שומר shomer, you're
still responsible and your responsibility means you pay the owner and you
get reimbursed from the גנב. ganav. That's a שומר שכר. shomer sachar.
But a שומר חנם shomer chinam. can choose which one he wants
to do. And presumably this case was a שומר חנם. shomer chinam,
So he says why are you telling this case that he has
to pay and get the money back from the גנב, ganav, and
a שומר חנם, he can choose to take a שבועה shvua and
let the owner deal with the גנב? ganav? אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
התם גברי דפרמיסתקא הוו. hatam gavrei deparmustaka havu. There the people
were around him, there were like people from the government, there were
police officers. דאי רמי קלא הוו אתו ומצלו
ליה. De'ei rami kala havu atu umatzlu lei. That he could have
just yelled and had the police officers come and helped him. So
therefore you were really negligent. And since you were really negligent in
that case, you pay the owner and you go get reimbursed from
the גנב ganav and not the other way around. But what's really
interesting about this last case is is that even in a case
of אונס, ones, it's not like if it's an אונס ones it's
not my responsibility. Right? If it's an אונס, ones, you're פטור patur
to pay, okay, but but in this case where you can get
reimbursed, you might actually have to pay the owner and then work
to get reimbursed from the גנב. ganav. Okay. All right, it's already
8:30. Can
people just give me two more minutes? I can get to the
top of the next page, but I told my substitute for tomorrow,
my wife, that we would start at the top of the next
page. So if just give me two more minutes, we'll read this
very quickly.
זאב אחד אינו אונס. Zeev echad eino ones. One wolf is not
an אונס. ones. שני זאבים אונס. Shenei zeevim ones. Two are. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, בשעת משלחת זאבים, bish'at mishlachat zeevim, when
the wolves
are running wild, אף זאב אחד אונס, af zeev echad ones, even
one is an אונס. ones. שני כלבים אינו אונס. Shenei kelavim eino
ones. Two dogs is not. ידוע הבבלי אומר משום רבי מאיר, Yadu'a
HaBavli omer mishum Rabbi Meir, מרוח אחת אינו אונס, miruach achat eino
ones, if they're coming from one direction it's not. משתי רוחות אונס,
Mishtei ruchot ones, if they're coming from two directions then they're coming
at you at different directions then you couldn't have done anything. You're
the shepherd here. הליסטים, Halistim, bandits, הרי זה אונס. harei zeh ones.
That's an אונס. ones. Presumably they're armed bandits. הארי הדוב והנמר והברדלס
והנחש. Ha'ari hadov vehanamer vehabardelas vehanachash. See I want to stay because
it has my name here. The lion, the bear, the נמר, namer,
which is what, the leopard? The ברדלס, bardelas, which is I think
the hyena, the snake. And they come they attack the flock. הרי
אלו אונס. Harei elu ones. That's an אונס. ones. אימתי? Eimatai? When
is that true? בזמן שבאו מאליהם. Bezman sheba'u me'aleihem. If they came
to you and you didn't do anything to make it happen. אבל
הוליכן למקום גדודי חיה וליסטים, Aval holichan limkom gedudei chaya ulistim, if
you stupidly brought your flock to a place where there are wild
animals or where there are bandits that are likely to be there,
אינו אונס. eino ones. It's not an אונס. ones. מתה כדרכה הרי
זה אונס. Meta kedarkah harei zeh ones. If it dies naturally, it's
an אונס. ones. סגפה ומתה, Sigfah umetah, if you sort of afflicted
it and it died. You gave it some lashes. אינו אונס. Eino
ones. Not much of a חידוש chiddush there. עלתה לראשי צוקים ונפלה
הרי זה אונס. Alta l'roshei tzukim venafela harei zeh ones. If it
went up to the top of the cliff and fell off, הרי
זה אונס. harei zeh ones. העלה לראשי צוקים ונפלה ומתה אינו אונס.
He'elah l'roshei tzukim venafela umetah eino ones. If you brought it up
to the head of the cliff, אינו אונס. eino ones. Okay, that
was fun. והתניא, Vehatanya, זאב אחד אונס. zeev echad ones.
How could you say only two wolves are an אונס? ones? We
have a ברייתא braita that says one is an אונס. ones. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, הוא בשעת משלחת.
hu bish'at mishlachat. משלחת זאבים, mishlachat ze'evim, that's at the time when
the wolves are running wild, רבי יהודה היא, Rabbi Yehuda hi, and
that's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the משנה. ליסטים הרי זה אונס,
Listim harei zeh ones, armed bandits is אונס. ones. So we don't
yet assume he's armed, I added the word armed. So the גמרא
says אמאי, amai, why is that true? לוקי גברא להדי גברא, lokei
gavra lahadei gavra, it's one against one! So what, some bandit comes
against you, you stand and protect. Now are you really supposed to
risk your life or your health to protect the flock? I mean,
I don't know what the גמרא thinks. אמר רב בליסטים מזויין, Amar
Rav be-listim mezuyan, he's armed. So until then we assumed, is ליסטים
listim singular?
I know, because it's really ליסטיס. listis.
It's ליסטיס listis and then it became ליסטים listim and then it
became מזויינין. mezuyanin. It's really ליסטיס מזויין. listis mezuyan. But anyway, but
you're right, here it's clear that it's one. It says one against
one. It's an excellent point. Okay, anyway, it should be ליסטיס. listis.
Anyway, the funny thing is okay, but when we thought he wasn't
armed, so what? So some guy comes and he attacks you, you're
supposed to risk breaking, you know, having your arm broken, like what?
Maybe yes, you're a שומר, you know. It's like whenever you see
it like, you know, whenever you see these things about like somebody
breaks into a bank and there's like this ten dollar an hour
rent-a-cop, you know, who's sort of there at the bank, like he
all of a sudden starts protecting. He's like, okay, is this worth
his ten dollars an hour to be risking his life? But like,
this is what you're being paid! So yes, when that happens, you
do what you need to do, you know. So yes, you're supposed
to risk, you know, you're supposed to go and fight the guy.
But if he's armed, then you don't have to fight him. So
איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they asked, ליסטיס מזויין ורועה מזויין, listis mezuyan
ve-ro'eh mezuyan, let's say the shepherd is equally armed as the robber.
This is the case of the armed guard, right, at the bank.
So מאי, mai, do we say you're supposed to now, you know,
protect? מי אמרינן אוקי גברא להדי גברא, mi amrinan okei gavra lahadei
gavra, it's one against one and you have to protect? או דלמא
האי מסר נפשיה והאי לא מסר נפשיה? o dilma hai masar nafshai
ve-hai lo masar nafshai? No, no, no. The גנב ganav came to
risk his life, he knew he was risking his life. You never
bought into this to agree to risk your life.
ומסתברא דהאי מסר נפשיה והאי לא מסר נפשיה. u-mistabra de-hai masar nafshai
ve-hai lo masar nafshai. That makes sense, that if he's armed you
do not have to protect. You could always choose not to and
just pay, right? Nobody is obligating you to risk your life. But
the point is here, even by choosing not to, you don't have
to protect. You're not reasonably expected to protect against somebody who's armed
even if you're equally armed. Okay, I assume you could explicitly contract
otherwise. If you really want to hire armed guards to protect the
Hope Diamond, you know, you can tell them you gotta, you know,
you gotta do what you gotta do. אמר ליה אביי לרבא, Amar
lei Abaye le-Rava, last line, אשכחיה רועה ואמר ליה, ashkechei ro'eh ve-amar
lei, let's say a shepherd came to a known גנב ganav and
said, גנבא סריא, ganva sarya, you rotten
גנב, ganav, בדוכתא פלניא יתבינן, be-duchta planya yatbinan, we're over there with
this big flock over at that place on the river, כמה גברי
איכא בהדן, kama gavrei ika bahadan, you shouldn't even think of coming
against us, we have a hundred people, we have so many people
בהדן bahadan
we have with
us, כמה כלבי איכא בהדן, kama kalbei ika bahadan,
we have so many dogs, כמה זוקספייא פסיקי לן, kama zukaspayei psiki
lan, we have so many like slingshots, and what a... what a
שייגעץ sheigetz you are thinking you're coming to attack us. ואזל ושקל
מיניה, ve-azal ve-shakal minei, so then he says thanks for the
information, and he came later and attacked them and he stole the
sheep. מאי, what's the הלכה? אמר ליה הרי הוליכן למקום גדודי חיה
וליסטים, Amar lei harei holichan le-makom gedudei chaya ve-listim,
that's like bringing them right to where there are animals and robbers,
so of course you're going to be חייב. chayav. You led the
robber to you, it's like leading the sheep to the robber.